<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Preprints | Davide Trotta</title><link>https://trottadavide.github.io/preprint/</link><atom:link href="https://trottadavide.github.io/preprint/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Preprints</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 23 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://trottadavide.github.io/media/icon_hu1ba24ac52fe1ca888ff07b91a7a34143_3408_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>Preprints</title><link>https://trottadavide.github.io/preprint/</link></image><item><title>A characterization of regular and exact completions of pure existential completions</title><link>https://trottadavide.github.io/preprint/preprint_3/</link><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://trottadavide.github.io/preprint/preprint_3/</guid><description>&lt;p>The notion of existential completion in the context of Lawvere&amp;rsquo;s doctrines was introduced by the second author in his PhD thesis, and it turned out to be a restriction to faithful fibrations of Peter Hofstra&amp;rsquo;s construction used to characterize Dialectica fibrations. The notions of regular and exact completions of elementary and existential doctrines were brought up in recent works by the first author with F. Pasquali and P. Rosolini, inspired by those done by M. Hyland, P. Johnstone and A. Pitts on triposes. Here, we provide a characterization of the regular and exact completions of (pure) existential completions of elementary doctrines by showing that these amount to the $ð—‹ð–¾ð—€/ð—…ð–¾ð—‘$ and $ð–¾ð—‘/ð—…ð–¾ð—‘$-completions, respectively, of the category of predicates of their generating elementary doctrines. This characterization generalizes a previous result obtained by the first author with F. Pasquali and P. Rosolini on doctrines equipped with Hilbert&amp;rsquo;s Ïµ-operators. Relevant examples of applications of our characterization, quite different from those involving doctrines with Hilbert&amp;rsquo;s Ïµ-operators, include the regular syntactic category of the regular fragments of first-order logic (and his effectivization) as well as the construction of Joyal&amp;rsquo;s Arithmetic Universes.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Categorifying computable reducibilities</title><link>https://trottadavide.github.io/preprint/preprint_2/</link><pubDate>Sat, 10 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://trottadavide.github.io/preprint/preprint_2/</guid><description>&lt;p>This paper discusses categorical formulations of the Medvedev, Muchnik and Weirauch reducibilities in Computability Theory and connects these reducibilities to different Lawvere categorical doctrines. These specific doctrines were used in previous work to provide categorical models for Dialectica logical properties. We relate Medvedev and Weyrauch doctrines to the Dialectica doctrine, showing that all these doctrines can be conceptualized in terms of (logic) quantifier (existential and universal) completions.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>An algebraic approach to the completions of elementary doctrines</title><link>https://trottadavide.github.io/preprint/preprint_1/</link><pubDate>Sat, 07 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://trottadavide.github.io/preprint/preprint_1/</guid><description>&lt;p>We provide a thorough algebraic analysis of three known completions having a central role in the exact completions of Lawvere&amp;rsquo;s doctrines, the one adding comprehensive diagonals (i.e. forcing equality on terms to coincide with the equality predicate), the one adding full comprehensions and the one adding quotients. We show that all these 2-adjunctions are 2-monadic and that the 2-monads arising from these adjunctions are all property-like. This entails that comprehensive diagonals, full comprehensions and quotients are algebraic properties of an elementary doctrine. Finally, we discuss and present the distributive laws between these 2-monads.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>